# Sergei Shilko



# Creativity is intelligence having fun - Albert Einstein

#### About

# 9

Berlin 12627

 $\square$ 

contact@sshilko.com

**()** 

sshilko.com

O

sshilko

in

sergeyshilko

#### **AWS**

EC2

**ELB** 

Lambda

**S**3

**RDS** 

ElastiCache

**VPC** 

CloudFront

Route 53

**API** Gateway

CodeCommit

CodeBuild

CodeDeploy

CodePipeline

CloudWatch

IAM

**ECR** 

Cognito

Certificate Manager

WAF & Shield

SQS

SNS

Mobile Hub

**PinPoint** 

WorkMail

Organizations

DynamoDB

Secrets Manager

### Backend

Golang

PHP

MySQL

Redis

Percona

# Summary

I'm engineer with hands-on experience in backends, REST & RPC APIs, AWS cloud certified. Skilled with online social networks, realtime chat, video call, online booking, accounting & billing, search, online payments, fraud & risk systems. Proficient with Docker, AWS, PHP, Golang.

### Experience

# MessageBird B.V.

June 2022 - Present

Senior Software Engineer - Billing & Accounting, Foundations (Go, K8s, AWS, GCP, PHP8) www.messagebird.com

Working on foundation services built with Go, K8s, PHP, AWS, GCP: accounts, accounting, billing, payments.

- REST APIs, OpenAPI v3, Google GRPC & protobuf APIs both in PHP8 and Golang 1.20
- Backend apps for message delivery over different channels: SMS, MMS, Voice, WhatsApp, Viber...
- Microservice architecture, platform services, product services, laC, event bus, api-first, domain-driven design
- Customer UI portal improvements to authentication: adopt JWT tokens, reworked containers startup/shutdown, unit-test coverage
- Define and adopt SLO, SLI, alerting with Prometheus, Thanos & Graphana dashboards
- CP Billing & Accounting runtime with >5000 RPS billing OLTP workers high load async billing
- Optimized high-load billing k8s cluster runtime performance, resulted in 60% cost reduction: opencensus, lightstep, jaeger
- Optimized speed of Gitlab CI/CD pipelines for K8s deployments: gitlab, docker, k8s, helm
- MEP billing, accounting, invoicing, pricing, quoting features in globally distributed multi-region app: golang/echo.v4, dynamodb/single-table
- Accounting security features like 2FA, SSO, reCaptcha, rate-limiting ...
- CPQ Quoting and Pricing project: set of APIs for self-serve application for creating custom enterprise sales offers

# **Tripod Technlogy GmbH**

June 2016 - February 2022

Head of Engineering at Tandem Language Exchange App www.tandem.net

Leaderhip and hands-on role, 1M DAU, 12+ Engineers, 50+ employees, education domain. Microservices applications, grow & manage team, analytics, business continuity. Building and running software at scale.

- Scaled backend infrastructure from 1000 RPM to 80000 RPM, from 100kDAU to >1mDAU and <50ms API response time</li>
- Scaled backend capacity from 1000's of users to >15M users
- Applied cost savings plans and utilized AWS Spot instances to reduce costs by 32%
- Hired multiple AI/ML, Data, Backend and devOPS engineers.
- Migrated monolithic backend application into 15 independent services
- Introduced Golang & AWS Keyspaces/Cassandra, DynamoDB for highload group chat application storage
- Promoted AWS Best Practices, executed AWS Well-Architected framework together with AWS solution architects
- Managed >40 EC2 servers across 3 AWS regions, migrated from AWS EC2 Classic to AWS VPC
- Updated codebase from PHP5 to PHP 7.4, Go 1.14 Docker 19, PHPUnit 9
- Supervised development of serverless microservices in Java/Kotlin/Golang & DynamoDB
- Split monorepository into >30 separate repositories with separate CI/CD
- Executed multiple refactoring projects in code, infrastructure, raw storage and databases
- Maintained backend roadmap and technology radar techradar opensource tandem net based on ThoughtWorks
- Improved user retention analytics, subscriptions and overall revenue tracking
- Updated realtime messaging server RabbitMQ, secured authorization, added 3rd websocket/MQTT browser client
  Added support for in-app purchase gifting, subscription hold, grace

SphinxSearch ManticoreSearch Docker

K8s

Beanstalkd

RabbitMQ

**AMQP** 

**MQTT** 

**Puppet** 

Nginx

Git

**PHPUnit** 

NewRelic APM

DataDog

HAProxy

Gitlab CI

Symfony

Graphana

Prometheus

**AWS** 

**GCS** 

Terraform

# Leadership, SDM, SDLC

Scrum

Agile

Team Lead

Project Manager

Head of Engineering

Backlog, Roadmap,

Delivery

Hiring

Budgeting

Team building

Cross functional teams

Mentoring

Jira

Confluence

C4 Model

# Languages

English (Fluent)

German (B2 - Advanced)

### Interests

# **Events**

Berlin - AWS Summit 2014, 2015, 2016, 2017, 2019 KubeCon + CloudNativeCon 2018, 2019

# Podcasts, Forums, Interests

Golang radio-t.com 2014 -2021 Habr habr.com 2008 - 2020

AWS Podcast 2016 - 2022

periods, geo-search.

- Increased application infrastructure and performance/APM monitoring automation and alerting via NewRelic
- Built full CI/CD pipeline on AWS Pipeline inc. Blue/Green deployments and AWS ASG/AutoScaling
- Improved China & SEA connectivity via transparent HAProxy, ICP/Hosting issues resolved
- Built internal business KPI, retention, engagement and revenue tracking systems
- Enforced PHPUnit & integration testing, code reviews & code style policies
- Migrated application services into containers (Docker)

# **Tripod Technlogy GmbH**

June 2013 - June 2016

Senior FullStack Software Developer at Tandem Language Exchange App www.tandem.net

Mature backend solutions for audio/video (tele)communications software. Developed public API for mobile clients.

- Implemented public API for native mobile clients
- Refactored old MVP prototype codebase
- Launched first production release 1.0
- Celebrated first 50 users sign-up on GA and first promotions on iTunes
- Deprecated legacy on-premise hosting and migrated into AWS EC2-Classic
- Celebrated '2015 Most innovative app of the year' award (Apple iTunes)
- Implemented PHP framework with open-source components
- Reduced API response times from >=2000ms to ~100ms
- Implemented critical app functionality: in-app messenger, real-time chat, community live feed, email-reminders, user search and more

#### Yangutu LLC

November 2011 - November 2012

Lead Software Developer at Yangutu LLC meetville.com

Working on web based social network.

- Added API for supporting external 3rd party Game-platform add-on's
- Added AMF Flex/ActionScript API Server for import/export of data to mobile platform
- Added Facebook, Instagram, VK and other social networks integrations
- Extended user data import and export API's

# eHarmony, Inc

August 2008 - September 2011

Software Engineer at eHarmony Inc www.eharmony.com

eHarmony Reporting and Management Tools for Risk Management team.

- Developed CMS/RMS Internal service from specification to manage and automate risks and fraud detection
- Working with sensitive client payment information
- Extended CMS/RMS service with flexible and configurable multi-role authentication system for different regions
- Added support for localization and translation of CMS/RMS
- Added analytics and audit tools for tracking and optimizing team (users or the CMS/RMS) performance

# **IponWeb**

August 2007 - September 2011

Software Engineer at IponWeb www.iponweb.com

 ${\sf SOAP/Rest\,API\,for\,real\text{-}time\,AD\,Exchange\,platform\,-\,RightMedia}$ 

- Worked on SOAP-API for high-load real-time advertising platform at scale
- Heavily extended and rewrote existing funtional test coverage, integrational e2e testing
- Covered many new edge cases in tests which lead to fixes in critical API parts

# Yahoo!

May 2008 - March 2009

Software Engineer at Yahoo! yahoo.com

AD Exchange API - RightMedia

 Refactoring tests, code and documentation, working with remote Yahoo developers team. SOAP API. Perl. PHP5

#### Education

# Grodnenski Dzjaržauny Universitet

September 2005 - September 2010

MSc Psychologe Pädagoge Experimental psychology

The WAN Show 2019 - 2023 UWP by Umputun 2016 -

Tom's Hardware

2021

agilemanifesto.org

12factor.net Investment Startups Crypto

# Reading

Management

Agile Scrum Sci-Fi Fantasy Horror Clean Code **TDD** 

Architecting for the Cloud

Isaac Asimov Robert Heinlein George Orwell Terry Goodkind Alan Kuper Tom DeMarco

Robert Martin: Clean Code: A Handbook of Agile Software Craftsmanship Adrenaline Junkies and Template Zombies: **Understanding Patterns of Project Behavior** 

**Edward Yourdon Death** March

Alan Kuper The Inmates Are Running the Asylum **Smart and Gets Things** Done: Joel Spolsky`s Concise Guide to Finding the **Best Technical Talent** Frederick P. Brooks, The Mythical Man-Month

E. Gamma Design Patterns. Elements of Reusable Object-Oriented Software

I. Hank Rainwater Herding Cats: A Primer for Programmers Who Lead **Programmers** 

Allan Kelly: Xanpan Designing Data-Intensive Applications: The Big Ideas Behind Reliable, Scalable,

and Maintainable System Jinesh Varia: AWS Architecting for the Cloud: Best practices

The Phoenix Project: A Novel About IT by Gene Kim, Kevin Behr, George Spafford

SCRUM The Art of Doing Twice the Work in Half the Time by Jeff Sutherland

The soul of a new machine by Tracy Kidder

The five dysfunctions of a team: a Leadership fable by Patrick Lencioni

Crossing the chasm: marketing and selling hightech products to mainstream customers The Deadline: A Novel about **GGPEK Elektrotechnik College**September 2000 - September 2005 Electrical Engineering Elektrische Energietechnik (Power engineering)

#### **Awards**

**Ultimate Go** Certificate #1latfj6ukq

**AWS Certified Solutions Architect - Associate (SAA)** 

Certificate #3GV5K7KKC14Q17W1

**AWS Certified Cloud Practitioner** 

Certificate #3B28554BK2EQ1PSD

Telc Deutsch B1 Zertifikat

Certificate #0503718

Project Management by Tom DeMarco

Solid Code: Optimizing the Software Development Life Cycle by Donis Marshall and John Bruno

The software development edge: essay on managing successful projects by Joe Marasco

Joel on software by Joel Spolsky

Why software sucks... adn what you can do about it by David S. Platt

Programming Collective Intelligence by Toby Segaran

97 things every software architect should know: collective wisdom from the Experts